<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
	<channel>
		<title></title>
		<description>Things that occur to me</description>
		<link>/</link>
		<atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>Exploration in Docker Bridging</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve been interested to look at with docker is the network setup. By default when you bring up a docker container you get a network interface with a private IP address which can communicate with other containers on that network and can make outbound connections to the wider world, but isn’t visible to the wider network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Docker does this by attaching the container to a bridge on the host and setting up iptables NAT rules to allow traffic to flow from this bridged network to the wider external network.  There’s a couple of downsides to this approach.  Firstly you need to explicitly specify inbound ports at container launch time if you want to have server services receive connections.  When you do this, docker sets up port-forwarding to allow that traffic into the container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with this approach is that if you’re running a service that sets ports up on the fly or which may change port during it’s runtime (e.g. metasploit) this is a bit on the inflexible side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other downside is the use of NAT, which can cause issues with some networking tools that make a large number of network connections (e.g. nmap).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option to address this is to use the docker option &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-net=host&lt;/code&gt; which essentially has the container run with the hosts network settings.  However one slight problem there is…. it doesn’t work with user namespaces, which I’m keen on having enabled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So ideally I’d like another option which provides no-NAT access to a container, ideally with an IP address on the host network subnet, with user namespaces enabled.  This is kind of similar to the VMWare Workstation/fusion setup with bridged networking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had quite a dig around in the official docker documentation to see if this kind of setup is possible using in-built functionality and I didn’t see a way of doing this, so a little manual work is required. However I did find some interesting references to working out this kind of problem notably this &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/25529386/how-can-i-set-a-static-ip-address-in-a-docker-container&quot;&gt;StackOverflow post&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.oddbit.com/2014/08/11/four-ways-to-connect-a-docker/&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; slightly older post on Docker networking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First in one shell we need to start our target container.  We use the option &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;--net=none&lt;/code&gt; to setup the container without having docker do it’s usual network setup routines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker run -it --net=none --name=nettest ubuntu:14.04 /bin/bash&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we need to create our virtual interface as below, I’ve called it &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;virtual0&lt;/code&gt; , in my case &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;eno16777736&lt;/code&gt; is the name of my host ethernet interface&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo ip link add virtual0 link eno16777736 type macvlan mode bridge&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we’re done that we need to add the virtual0 interface to the container, so we need to know the pid, which we can get from docker inspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker inspect --format &#39;{ { .State.Pid }}&#39; nettest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we create a link in /var/run/netns and set the netns of the virtual0 interface to be the same as our container.  In the examples below 3463 is the pid returned by the docker inspect command above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo mkdir -p /var/run/netns&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo ln -s /proc/3463/ns/net /var/run/netns/3463&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo ip link set virtual0 netns 3463&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can then bring up the interface and apply an IP address.  Doing this inside the container doesn’t work from a permissions standpoint so it can be done with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ip netns exec&lt;/code&gt; command from the host&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo ip netns exec 3463 ip link set virtual0 up&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we can then assign a DHCP address from the host network DHCP server to the container&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo ip netns exec 3463 dhclient virtual0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously doing all this manually is likely to be a bit much trouble for most use-cases, but I think with a bit of automation it could come in handy for some tasks which need a bit more flexibility in networking than the default docker configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit:&lt;/strong&gt; I did find &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gopher-net/macvlan-docker-plugin&quot;&gt;this project&lt;/a&gt; which looks to address the same problem, but at the moment it doesn’t seem to work for me…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit2:&lt;/strong&gt; Well that was quick. The problems I had with the macvlan docker plugin got fixed (thanks to @nerdalert), so for a faster/less manual solution to this problem I’d recommend having a look at the link in the first edit!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2016 14:45:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2016/02/07/Exploration-in-Docker-bridging/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/02/07/Exploration-in-Docker-bridging/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Docker 1.10 Notes - User Namespaces</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;So Docker 1.10 has just landed and with it a number of great new security enhancements.  One of the main ones is the enabling of User Namespaces.  This adds an extra level of protection as processes running in a container as root will not be running as root on the host Operating System, which makes it harder for a rogue process to break out of the container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I downloaded 1.10 as an upgrade to an existing 1.9.1 install on Ubuntu, I noticed that User Namespaces don’t seem to be enabled by default, so I thought it would be worth noting how I enabled it as it’s a handy feature to be running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get this working on Ubuntu 15.10, which uses systemd, I did this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;copy the base systemd config file to /etc/systemd/system&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo cp /lib/systemd/system/docker.service /etc/systemd/system/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not likely to be a good idea to modify the one in /lib/systemd/system/ as it could be overwritten by later package downloads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve done that you need to tell docker to remap the userns.  This can be done to an explicitly chosen uid:gid, but the basic default option will probably work fine for a lot of use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in /etc/systemd/system/docker you can edit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ExecStart=/usr/bin/docker daemon -H fd://&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ExecStart=/usr/bin/docker daemon --userns-remap=default -H fd://&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then restart docker with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo systemctl daemon-reload&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo systemctl restart docker&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve done that you can check to make sure that it’s working by running a process in a container as root and look at what UID is being shown on the host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker run -it ubuntu:14.04 top&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;should run the top process as root in the container and you can then do ps -ef or similar on the host OS and check what UID is in use.  In my example if came out looking like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;165536     2347   2323  0 21:20 pts/0    00:00:00 top&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no longer running as root , yay!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One quick thing I noticed is that a side-effect of enabling userns-remap was that all my downloaded images were no longer visible, so I had to re-download the one’s I had.  So it’s defintely worth trying this change out on test systems before rolling out to production!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can back up your existing images with something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker save&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;if needed and it’s also worth noting that if you disable userns again, your original images will be available.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 20:30:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2016/02/04/Docker-User-Namespaces/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/02/04/Docker-User-Namespaces/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Is This Thing on </title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the perenial problems of being an infrequent blogger is of course, you forget exactly how you used to do things…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this post is just to make sure I’ve actually remembered how this is all set-up before I write something more substantive :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 31 Jan 2016 19:36:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2016/01/31/is-this-thing-on/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2016/01/31/is-this-thing-on/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Set-up a Complete Security Test Environment with One Command and Docker Compose</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Following on from my last post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://raesene.github.io/blog/2015/07/23/using-docker-for-security-testing/&quot;&gt;Using Docker for Security Testing&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it would be interesting to see if we can set-up an even more automated environment by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.docker.com/docker-compose&quot;&gt;Docker Compose&lt;/a&gt;.  Docker Compose is a means of creating a linked set of containers, which you can configure to be started up together, so useful where you want to make use of multiple systems at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the use case of Security Testing I was thinking it would be nice to have containers which provide a service that you connect to over a network port, for example &lt;a href=&quot;http://dradisframework.org/&quot;&gt;Dradis&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openvas.org/&quot;&gt;OpenVAS&lt;/a&gt;, alongside your main command line driven container which has tools that you’re more likely to use interactively on a test, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://nmap.org/&quot;&gt;Nmap&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rapid7/metasploit-framework&quot;&gt;Metasploit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out this is relatively straightforward using Docker Compose.  You can set-up a yml file with information on the containers you want to instantiate (the default name is docker-compose.yml) and then just spin that up with a single command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for this setup the Docker Compose file looks like this&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
sectest:
  image: raesene/sectest
  command: /bin/bash
  links:
     - dradis
     - openvas
dradis: 
  image: raesene/auto-docker-dradis
  ports: 
      - &quot;3000:3000&quot;
  command: bundle exec rails server
openvas:
  image: mikesplain/openvas
  ports:
      - &quot;443:443&quot;
      - &quot;9390:9390&quot;
      - &quot;9391:9391&quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file defines three containers that we’re going to use.  The first one is an instance of a basic Security Testing container that I created &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/raesene/sectest&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.  There’s nothing too major in there it just sets up some tools that I commonly use on reviews.  In that first stanza we specify that the dradis and openvas containers are linked to that one, which is relevant when we start things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next section we start up the dradis container and here it’s worth noting two points.  The first is the “ports” command.  This sets up port mappings so that the service will be visible on the docker host, which is where we’ll be connecting to it from.  The second thing to note is the “command” directive which just specifies what should be run when the container comes up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third section we specify the openvas container and set-up some port mappings to expose the relevant ports to the host.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we’ve got this file created we just need to start things up.  The command I’ve used for this is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
docker-compose run --service-ports sectest /bin/bash
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this does is start-up the sectest container and any linked containers (which is why it was important to add those links in the docker-compose.yml file), also the –service-ports option is specified so that the ports will be exposed, and lastly we specify the commmand to run, in this case /bin/bash.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all goes well this should download and start-up all three containers and you should have a command prompt in the sectest container, along with started accessible services for the other two containers.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2015 20:06:39 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/08/15/set-up-a-complete-security-test-environment-with-command-and-docker-compose/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/08/15/set-up-a-complete-security-test-environment-with-command-and-docker-compose/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Using Docker for Security Testing</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Following on from my &lt;a href=&quot;http://raesene.github.io/blog/2015/07/05/some-notes-on-docker/&quot;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; about Docker, I’ve been giving some thoughts to how I could make use of this in my day-to-day work of security testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a couple of areas where I can see Docker being quite useful, mainly due to the ease of maintaining and installing applications and also the reduced resource utilization over “tradtional” virtual machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first one is in isolating security testing applications which require a bit of setup or a particular environment to operate in.  Some very useful security testing tools are slightly more complex to setup and run than just doing a  &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; of the repo and running a script and there can always be conflicts in the version of underlying tools and libraries required for them to run. These tools can benefit from the isolation that using a containerized version brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Already on &lt;a href=&quot;https://hub.docker.com&quot;&gt;Docker Hub&lt;/a&gt; you can see a number of containers avaiable which do this for you.  An example is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openvas.org/&quot;&gt;OpenVAS&lt;/a&gt; for which there are a number of containers available, for example &lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/mikesplain/openvas/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the nice things about containers built using the automated build approach is that Docker Hub will show you the dockerfile used to build the container, which provides some level of transparancy over what you’re downloading (and the syntax is relatively basic, so easy to see what’s going on).  You still obviously have to trust Docker Hub and the sources of data used to build the container, which may not be applicable to some environments, and there a better option might be an internal docker repository with internally validated builds.  Even there, the Docker Hub examples are useful to base your Dockerfiles on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way in which containers can be handy is in creating new, consistent, security test environments for each piece of work done.  A common problem in security testing is ensuring that your testing environment is clear of any data from previous reviews, to avoid inadvertant contamination and also ensuring that your tools are regularly updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a containerized image as your base here is quite straightforward as you just get an image, and then create a new container based on that image for each review.  I’ve started a sample one &lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/raesene/sectest/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; which shows some of the basic tools.  The Dockerfile is on github &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/raesene/sectest&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and could be useful as a starting point for others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you could replicate this with virtual machines, but the downside there is that the disk space requirements for a new VM per test would be pretty hefty and cloning/starting a new VM can be a bit slow, when compared to containers.  Depending on the type of testing you do, you may need the more complete environemnt that a VM provides, but I reckon for a lot of  testing a container should work just fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another potential advantage of this approach is that you could archive off the container at the end of the test which could make reproducing findings at a later date simpler (less risk of tools updates changing the results of a test)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-other-security-testing-containers&quot;&gt;Some Other Security Testing Containers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned before there are quite a few containers turning up on Docker Hub which could be useful, here’s some of the ones I’ve seen so far&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/raesene/auto-docker-dradis/&quot;&gt;Dradis community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/owasp/zap2docker-stable/&quot;&gt;OWASP ZAP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/kalilinux/kali-linux-docker/&quot;&gt;Kali Linux&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/wpscanteam/wpscan/&quot;&gt;WPScan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 20:56:47 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/07/23/using-docker-for-security-testing/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/07/23/using-docker-for-security-testing/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Some notes on docker</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been spending some time this weekend looking more at docker and where I think it could be useful for my workflows, and along the way I’ve learned a couple of things which I didn’t know, so I thought it would be worth recording them, in case they’re useful to others.  None of this is particularly earth shattering but hey could save someone some time :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;images-and-containers&quot;&gt;Images and Containers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First was the distinction between images and containers.  Images are what you build from (e.g. a template) containers are running instances of those images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;container-persistence&quot;&gt;Container Persistence&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do one of the canonical examples that’s provided in many tutorials&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
docker run -t -i ubuntu:latest /bin/bash
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You get an interactive shell prompt in a docker container.  If you exit that process you go back to the host and if you repeat the command you get another instance of the container, with none of the files you created in the first one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that you might get the impression that docker container filesystems are not persistent (i.e. when the exit all the data is lost), but that’s not the case from what I can see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get back into a container instance you’ve used previously you need to get the name or ID first.  To do that use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
docker ps -a
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which will list all the container instances you’ve ever run on that system and it’ll look something like&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
CONTAINER ID        IMAGE                        COMMAND                CREATED             STATUS                      PORTS                    NAMES
39c1e5cf8319        raesene/auto-docker-dradis   &quot;bundle exec rails s   47 minutes ago      Up 47 minutes               0.0.0.0:3000-&amp;gt;3000/tcp   cranky_kilby
e529903a3183        raesene/auto-docker-dradis   &quot;bundle exec rails s   55 minutes ago                                                           compassionate_yonath
f084aaca32ee        raesene/dradisframework      &quot;bundle exec rails s   24 hours ago        Exited (0) 47 minutes ago                            agitated_ptolemy
8a8f7b95082a        2bfb337a0aa8                 &quot;bundle exec rails s   24 hours ago        Exited (0) 24 hours ago                              fervent_hopper
8a2a0046b769        ruby:latest                  &quot;/bin/bash&quot;            24 hours ago        Exited (0) 24 hours ago                         	 compassionate_goodall
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from that you can see each container has an ID (the first column) and a name (the last column).  You can restart the container using either of those.  For example to restart the container with the name compassionate_goodall to get some files off it, you’d use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;
docker start compassionate_goodall
docker attach compassionate_goodall
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;docker-hub-build-options&quot;&gt;docker hub build options&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s two options for getting your builds onto docker hub.  The first is to get a container, make modifications to it on your own docker engine and then commit the changes back to your own repository on docker hub.  This works fine but is rather lacking in transparancy as to what went into the build and also doesn’t really lend to others participating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is using Docker Hub automated builds, where a github/bitbucket repository is created with the Dockerfile present and then Docker Hub handles the build in an automated fashion from that Dockerfile. &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.docker.com/docker-hub/builds/&quot;&gt;docker automated build docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exposing-docker-ports&quot;&gt;Exposing docker ports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default containers have no ports exposed the the host network and many containers do not have things like SSHD installed, so remote access isn’t there by default.  The best way to map a port from the host to the guest is when the docker run command is used with the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; option.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2015 20:10:15 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/07/05/some-notes-on-docker/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/07/05/some-notes-on-docker/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>So you're giving a conference talk</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;I realised the other day that I’ve been doing public speaking for quite a while now (started with doing internal training courses back in the 90’s, and graduated on to doing external speaking at seminars and conferences about 10 years back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over that time, I’ve inevitably made some mis-steps and also seen a number of others from speakers at conferences I’ve attended, so I thought it would be worth putting together some hints and tips for prospective speakers.  Hopefully some of these will be useful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treat your presentation like a story.&lt;/strong&gt; It should have a start, middle and an end. I find it helps to think of presentations in this way, as you can imagine the story your trying to tell and think about whether a particular slide fits into that part of the narrative or not. Think about “what am I trying to say, why should the audience care and what can they do about it”, and make sure your conclusion has some clear points or advice for next steps.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Don’t sweat presentation tool choice too much.&lt;/strong&gt;  A lot of people get very hung up on liking/disliking specific presentation tools (e.g. PowerPoint, Prezi, Keynote).  The simple fact is that I’ve seen good and bad presentations with every tool.  The important part is that you find one that suits your style and learn how to use it well.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoid walls of text in your presentation.&lt;/strong&gt;  This one is very common.  If you put a lot of dense text on your slides, people will naturally start reading that and not paying attention to what you’re saying.  There’s a natural desire to provide information for people after the talk but that can easily go in speaker notes, or a white paper, or a blog post.  It doesn’t need to go into the body of the slide.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Practice, Practice, Practice.&lt;/strong&gt; Timing a talk is really tricky to do.  The best way to address this is practice your talk.  Talk to yourself, your dog/cat, your partner, your friends, basically anyone who’ll listen.  I find that once I’ve delivered a talk a couple of times in this way, it’s easier to remember queues and the flow of the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker Note cards.&lt;/strong&gt;  Again this one gets a lot of pro/con feeling.  My advice is, if you feel you need prompt cards, use them.  But try to avoid just reading them one at a time.  Keep themes or key points on there, don’t put the exact words you want to say.  If you just read from cards, you won’t be able to engage your audience.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage your audience.&lt;/strong&gt;  So this is hard, especially if you’re not used to public speaking.  But it’s important to look up at your audience while you speak.  Try to look around, not just at one person.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demos (and the dark god).&lt;/strong&gt;  Live demos can help bring a topic to life and, when done right, can really help drive a point across.  With that said, they often fail, which can be pretty stressful in the middle of a presentation! I’ve had things which literally worked 30 minutes earlier, fail for no obvious reason. This happens so often that many presenters will refer to “The dark god of demos”!.  My recommendation for speakers who are starting out is to avoid them unless really necessary and always have a back-up option like a pre-recorded video.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fonts and colours.&lt;/strong&gt;  Watch out for this when presenting things like live coding or other demos.  Fonts and colour schemes which look good on your laptop may be totally unintelligible when up on a big screen.  In particular avoid dark backgrounds with coloured text, these rarely look good.  Also make sure you’re au-fait with the keyboard shortcuts for making text larger and smaller in your editor/IDE, as you will likely need to use them on the day…&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always develop your own material.&lt;/strong&gt;  It’s very hard to deliver someone else’s slide deck well.  I’ve seen a number of times where the presenter didn’t write their presentation, and sometimes didn’t seem to have read it either! This results in a rather disjointed delivery and inability to answer questions, which rarely ends well…  If you absolutely have to do this, make sure to read/understand the whole thing before delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lastly Enjoy yourself :).&lt;/strong&gt;  Public speaking can seem like a stressful thing to do, and everyone gets nervous when then present (well I do anyway) but it can be fun to explain your ideas to a group of people and in a lot of cases you’ll get some good feedback/ideas about what you could do next.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2015 13:16:12 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/05/23/so-youre-giving-a-conference-talk/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/05/23/so-youre-giving-a-conference-talk/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Some potential problems extrapolating from data in security</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;One of the perennial problems in security is the lack of hard data, so it’s been good to see over the last couple of years a growing number of reports coming out which seek to shed a bit more light on what’s happening in InfoSec.  One of the more prominent of these reports is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.verizonenterprise.com/DBIR/2015/&quot;&gt;Verizon Data Breach Investigation report&lt;/a&gt; and I always read it as it has some interesting insights into what’s happening in areas that I don’t get too much exposure too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However when I read this years report I noticed a section which looked .. well odd.  It’s on page 16 of the report and talks about the top 10 “exploited” vulnerabilities in 2014.  What struck me as very odd is the number of very old vulnerabilities in the list.  Eight of the ten issues listed are from 2002 or before.  Now I know IT security patching can be a bit slow, but this seems excessive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I had a look at the CVE references provided and what I found did not ehance my confidence that this data was an accurate reflection of exploited issues.  In a number of cases the referenced CVEs are for old and or obscure products that would surprise me if they’re in wide deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best example of this problem is &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2002-1931&quot;&gt;CVE-2002-1931&lt;/a&gt; which gets listed at number nine.  This is a Cross-Site Scripting issue in version 2.1.1 and 1.1.3 of a product called PHP Arena and specifically the pafileDB area of that product.  Now I struggled to find out too much about that product because the site that used to host it www.phparena.net is now a gambling site (I presume that the domain name lapsed and was picked up as it got decent traffic).  Searching via google for information, most of the results seemed to be from vulnerability databases(!) and using a google dork of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.co.uk/?gws_rd=ssl#q=inurl:pafiledb.php&amp;amp;start=170&quot;&gt;inurl:pafiledb&lt;/a&gt; shows a total of 156 results, which seems low for one of the most exploited issues on the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also looking at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.securityfocus.com/bid/6021&quot;&gt;this securityfocus page&lt;/a&gt; we can see that PHP Arena pafileDB 3.0 isn’t vulnerable to this issue and from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cvedetails.com/product/2451/Php-Arena-Pafiledb.html?vendor_id=1413&quot;&gt;this cvedetails page&lt;/a&gt; we can see that pafileDB 3.0 came out in 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for this issue to be in the top 10 most exploited issues on the Internet, we need a large number of people to not have updated a very exploitable, discontinued PHP forum product for 13 years…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I saw this initially, I thought “ahh must be a problem with the publishing”, so I contacted Verizon by e-mail and then &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/raesene/status/589022276252782592&quot;&gt;over twitter&lt;/a&gt;, however apparently not, this is the real data!  They were very nice and provided some additional detail (although it’s hard to be specific in 140 chars) which indicates that this data came from IDS sensors correlated to vulnerabilities, but I can’t really see how that could possibly be the case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it were just raw network IDS sensor data it’s possible if it were just looking at network traffic and alerting on vulnerability scanners testing for things, but a) that’s not exploitation of an issue, just scaning for its presence and b) even then things like the PHP arena one don’t make sense unless the IDS sensor is just mistakenly putting all XSS attempts into that bucket.  Either way I’m afraid this looks like mistaken interpretation of the available data and an extrapolation based on that interpretation&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do I care enough to write this?  Well unfortunately what a lot of people in the industry will do here is take the headline “97% of exploited issues came from these 10 issues” and use this to drive spending and other decisions, and that’s unfortunate as without looking at the detail you don’t realise that there are problems with that interpretation of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For completeness here’s some notes on the other issues.  The first two are generic SNMPv1 issues from 2002 which from their descriptions &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2002-0012&quot;&gt;CVE−2002−0012&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2002-0013&quot;&gt;CVE−2002−0013 &lt;/a&gt; look kind of like the same thing and also are not very specific as it’s multiple vendors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number three is default SNMP community strings &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-1999-0517&quot;&gt;CVE-1999-0517&lt;/a&gt; which is kind of believable as you do see a fair bit of SNMP out there, although in my recent experience default community strings on the Internet are rarer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number four is a memory leak DoS in Windows NT 4 and 2000 &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2001-0540&quot;&gt;CVE-2001-0540&lt;/a&gt; RDP requests. Now both these products have been out of support for some years and are less seen these days, also with a DoS issue whilst it’s possible to detect someone attacking it with network IDS, I don’t see how you’d easily detect actual exploitation without something running on the target server to note the service crashing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number five is a newer one, &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2014-3566&quot;&gt;POODLE&lt;/a&gt;.  This being in the top 10 exploited issues would be very interesting as traditionally SSL issues which require an active Man-In-The-Middle attack are considered less exploited (usually ‘cause if the person has a privileged position on the network like that, they can do far worse things that exploit SSL issues!).  Now I’d believe it was one of the top “scanned for “ issues but not exploited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number six is &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2012-0152&quot;&gt;another RDP DoS&lt;/a&gt; .  This one is more modern, but the problem of accurately detecting DoS exploitation remains..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number seven is a pretty obscure one &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2001-0680&quot;&gt;Directory traversal vulnerability in ftpd in QPC QVT/Net 4.0 and AVT/Term 5.0&lt;/a&gt;.  As with the PHP Arena, there’s not a lot of information on the Internet about this product.  the host company still exists but no download/version information seems easily available.  That said from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.securityfocus.com/bid/2618&quot;&gt;Securityfocus&lt;/a&gt; the latest affected OS is Windows 2000 SP2, which hasn’t been in support for a long time and has other critical exploitable issues, so I’d have guessed that if someone was going to exploit it they wouldn’t have targeted this issue…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number eight is a directory traversal issue in &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2002-1054&quot;&gt;Pablo FTP v1.0 build 9&lt;/a&gt; . From a quick search the product was up to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pablosoftwaresolutions.com/html/quick__n_easy_ftp_server.html&quot;&gt;version 3.2&lt;/a&gt; when it was last released and that version supports up to Windows vista, so it’s a fair guess that version 1 hasn’t been in use/supported for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number nine is the PHP Arena issue mentioned previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number ten is a bug in &lt;a href=&quot;http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2002-1932&quot;&gt;windows 2000 and XP&lt;/a&gt; where administrators aren’t notified if logs fill up. If a system isn’t patched for this they also have all the canonical remote code execution bugs like MS06-040 and MS08-067.  So for this to be more exploited, we have to have large numbers of attackers who want to fill up logs with impunity, instead of taking over the system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 18:08:34 +0100</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/04/17/some-potential-problems-extrapolating-from-data-in-security/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/04/17/some-potential-problems-extrapolating-from-data-in-security/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Software Library Repositories and Security</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Last week I did a presentation for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.securi-tay.co.uk&quot;&gt;Securi-Tay Conference&lt;/a&gt;.  The title of the talk was “Security and ‘modern’ software development”, and the main theme of the talk was looking at library repositories like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rubygems.org&quot;&gt;Rubygems&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npmjs.org&quot;&gt;npm&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nuget.org&quot;&gt;NuGet&lt;/a&gt; and how an attacker could try and place malicous content into those locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now nothing in this talk is particularly new as people have been talking about malicious library installs in &lt;a href=&quot;http://lanyrd.com/2013/rulu/scgxzr/&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://webinos.org/2013/06/17/reflections-on-nodejs-malware/&quot;&gt;npm&lt;/a&gt; amongst others for some time, however I do think that it’s still not a widely recognized problem and particularly as these repositories grow in size and use, we’re going to see more malicious content on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a fairly basic typo-squatting approach on PyPi was actually seen recently &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/Python/comments/2wr93b/this_one_looks_odd_doesnt_it/&quot;&gt;as noted on /r/python&lt;/a&gt;, which lasted for a while before it was noted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My initial reviews looked at areas like how package maintainers are authenticated to the repos, whether digital signing is supported and/or widely used, whether there is any curation on the repositories and some other associated areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most cases the picture at the moment isn’t particularly bright from a security standpoint, although initiatives like &lt;a href=&quot;http://theupdateframework.com/&quot;&gt;The Update Framework&lt;/a&gt; are trying to improve the situation, progress appears pretty difficult to make.  This isn’t particularly surprising as adding security is going to make development/publishing more awkward and at the moment I don’t think many developers see this trade-off as worth the added security benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway I have an expanded version of this talk planned for &lt;a href=&quot;http://2015.appsec.eu/&quot;&gt;OWASP AppSec EU&lt;/a&gt; in May, so I’ve got some experiments to try out between now and then to look at other aspects of Repository security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mention this specifically as I’m going to put a reference to this post into the description of various test libraries that I’m planning to write and if you’ve installed one and are wondering what the heck I’m up to, this will hopefully provide some information :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2015 21:05:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/03/01/software-library-repositories-and-security/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/03/01/software-library-repositories-and-security/</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Burp Passive Scanner Plugins with JRuby</title>
				<description>&lt;p&gt;Like most web application testers, I’m a fan of using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.portswigger.net&quot;&gt;Burp Suite&lt;/a&gt; for automation and generally making the process of completing a test a whole lot easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent versions the Portswigger team have opened up the Burp API and we’ve started to see more 3rd party plugins coming along which is awesome as it lets Burp users contribute, whilst making their own testing lives easier.  Plugins can be written in Java, Jython, or JRuby.  Looking at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pro.portswigger.net/bappstore&quot;&gt;BApp store&lt;/a&gt; most of the entries at the moment are either in Java or Jython, so I thought it was worth documenting a basic passive scanner check in JRuby as there are definitely a couple of gotchas to getting everything working, including one that had me stumped (thanks to Timur and Ryan for pointing me in the right direction!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up to use JRuby you need to point Burp at your JRuby jar file in the extender–&amp;gt; options tab, and after that you should be able to load an appropriately configured ruby file in the main Extensions window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code for this basic check is on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/raesene/burp_sample_plugins&quot;&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; so here are a couple of points to note.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First up there’s a load of information on the topic of Burp plugins on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.portswigger.net/search?updated-min=2012-01-01T00:00:00Z&amp;amp;updated-max=2013-01-01T00:00:00Z&amp;amp;max-results=16&quot;&gt;Portswigger blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general structure the basic plugin is a ruby class called BurpExtender, with a method which implements the callback (registerExtenderCallback) and for the passive scan we need a doPassiveScan method as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main meat of the check happens in doPassiveScan.  This method is called whenever Burp encounters a URL that it’s set to passively scan (either just URLs in scope or all URLs depending on the configuration you’ve set).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within that you can extract information about the request that triggered the call and analyze that information to see if an issue is present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the sample check we’re looking for an HTTP header, which if it’s not found, will add a low severity issue to the burp scanner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;def doPassiveScan(baseRequestResponse)
    service_info = baseRequestResponse.getHttpService()
    host_name = service_info.getHost()
    response_info = @helpers.analyzeResponse(baseRequestResponse.getResponse)
    headers = response_info.getHeaders()&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section of code extracts some information from the request-response object that Burp passes in to the method.  It’s pretty easy to extract the various parts of the HTTP request to analyze and once you’ve done it they appear as ruby objects (e.g. strings or arrays) which can be analyzed with standard ruby methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;header_found = false&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;headers.each do |header|
  if header.downcase =~ /your_value_here/
      header_found = true
  end
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the next section of code is really the only analysis that we’re doing in this basic example.  The headers variable is an array, so we can iterate over it and check each element to see if it’s found. In this case our header is called ‘your_value_here’ which is pretty unlikely to show up, but in a real check this could be replaced with something like ‘Strict-Transport-Security’ or ‘Public-Key-Pins’ to check for the presence of security related HTTP headers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we’ve got our finding of course the next step is to add it to the scanner results, so we’ll need to create a Scan Issue and pass it back to Burp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;findings = Java::JavaUtil::ArrayList.new&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line was one of the places I tripped up initially.  Burp expects an array of results back and not a single Scan issue so creating an array to hold the findings is handy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;finding_message = CustomHttpRequestResponse.new
finding_message.setResponse(baseRequestResponse.getResponse())
finding_message.setRequest(baseRequestResponse.getRequest())
finding_message.setHttpService(baseRequestResponse.getHttpService())
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section is necessary if you want to return the request/response information into the scanner and is another place where I had some issues. The key point is that you need to implement a class that conforms to the interface for the IHttpRequestResponse class that the Burp API describes.  In the file on github there’s a class that seems to work for me.  It looks a bit boilerplate heavy, but at the moment the more rubyish setup with attr_accessor helpers for the class properties doesn’t seem to fly for me, so manual getter/setter methods it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;unless header_found
  finding = CustomScanIssue.new
  finding.httpMessages=finding_message
  finding.httpService=baseRequestResponse.getHttpService()
  finding.url=@helpers.analyzeRequest(baseRequestResponse.getHttpService(), baseRequestResponse.getRequest).getUrl()
  finding.name = &quot;Header Not Set&quot;
  finding.detail = &quot;A header that should be set isn&#39;t&quot;
  finding.severity = &quot;Low&quot;
  finding.confidence = &quot;Certain&quot;
  finding.remediation_detail = &quot;Lorem Ipsum&quot;
  finding.issue_background = &quot;Sit Dolor Amet&quot;
  findings.add finding
end
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This code just populates another class which you need to implement which is the Scan Issue.  In general that class is pretty straight forward like the RequestResponse class but a key point is that Burp expects an array of RequestResponse issues to be returned in the messages property of the scan issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last bit in this basic example is a brief method to do some basic handling of duplicate instances of the same issue (saves the scanner repeatedly finding the same issue for a URL)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;``` ruby&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;def consolidateDuplicateIssues(existing_issue, new_issue)
    if existing_issue.getIssueName == new_issue.getIssueName
      return -1
    else
      return 0
    end
  end&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;```&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously quite a basic example but hopefully shows that once you know the structure of the code, implementing scanner checks in Burp should be a relatively straightforward task, and can have some cool benefits in terms of automating the testing process.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2015 20:45:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<link>/blog/2015/01/15/burp-passive-scanner-plugins-with-jruby/</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">/blog/2015/01/15/burp-passive-scanner-plugins-with-jruby/</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
